{"tossups": [{"question": "Quebec Governor Lord Dorchester was approached for assistance by one side during this event. A leader of this rebellion previously took part in the Groton Riots and was arrested near the Nashua River. Besides Job Shattuck, another leader of this rebellion worked with Luke Day, though William Shepard stopped them from taking Springfield Courthouse. Courts in Worcester were shut down by regulators during this event. For ten points, name this 1786 to 1787 rebellion in Massachusetts against tax collection by Revolutionary War Veterans.", "answer": "<b><u>Shays'</u></b> Rebellion (accept synonymous answers for \"Rebellion\" such as \"Uprising\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Leo von Klenze [[KLEN-zuh]] built a temple named for this place under the auspices of Ludwig of Bavaria, and included several busts of historical Germans. The legendary king Vanlandi visited this site in a work that describes a \"historical\" figure's law about the dead being burned and their ashes buried. The <em>Heimskringla</em> discusses that ritual for reaching this place, which is accomplished by Eric Bloodaxe, king of Norway, in an epic poem. For ten points, name this mythical hall of slain warriors that Norse pagans believed awaited them in the afterlife.", "answer": "<b><u>Valhalla</u></b> (or <b><u>Walhalla</u></b>; accept <b><u>Walhalla</u></b> Temple)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man's most significant expeditions were completed with assistance from his countryman Martin Spangberg. Dockyards in Okhotsk built the <em>Fortune</em>, a ship used by this explorer to undertake the First Kamchatka Expedition with support from Peter the Great. The Siberian coast was mapped by this explorer, who was temporarily shipwrecked off the Aleutian coast during a 1741 expedition. A strait separating Alaska from the Far East region of Russia is named for, for ten points, which Danish explorer?", "answer": "Vitus <b><u>Bering</u></b> (accept <b><u>Bering</u></b> Strait; or <b><u>Bering</u></b> Sea; or <b><u>Bering</u></b> Island)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "One of these items found at Takalik Abaj [[tah-KAH-leek AH-bah]] that was turned into an altar is the only one found outside a certain region. The material for these items was mined at La Cobata [[koh-BAH-tah]], and the distinct features of these items indicate they represent rulers of the culture that created them. A popular pseudo-historical theory argues the features of these items show \u201cAfrican influences.\u201d For ten points, name these distinctive artworks of the Mesoamerican \u201cmother-culture\u201d found at sites like San Lorenzo and La Venta.", "answer": "<b><u>Olmec</u></b> colossal <b><u>head</u></b>s (prompt on partial answers; accept synonymous answers such as Statues of <b><u>Olmec Head</u></b>s)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In this nation's mythology, a horned, transparent man known as the \"Divine Farmer\" introduced agricultural techniques and various drugs. The mother goddess of this nation's myth system, Nuwa, was a turtle who held the heavens and Earth on her back. This nation was created by the breath of Pangu with the help of the <em>Kirin</em> and the immortal Phoenix, and the first mythical king of its Xia [[SHAH]] dynasty was Yu the Great. For ten points, name this country whose populace was wiped out by a mythical great flood of its Yellow River.", "answer": "<b><u>China</u></b> (accept <b><u>Zhongguo</u></b>)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "John Edward McGilvrey was the first head of this university created by the Lowry Bill, and George Hammond created its plan. William Oxley Thompson opposed this school in the \"Credit War\" over transfer credits. Allison Krause and William Schroeder were killed at this university, where a Joseph Filo picture showed a screaming Mary Ann Vecchio. A protest at this university forced Ohio governor Jim Rhodes to ask for assistance from the National Guard. For ten points, name this university, where four students were shot dead during a 1970 Vietnam War protest.", "answer": "<b><u>Kent State</u></b> University (accept <b><u>Kent State</u></b> Massacre; or <b><u>Kent State</u></b> Shooting)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A puppet king of this city, Kandalanu, was installed after the previous puppet king led a rebellion. After destroying this city, the king Sennacherib supposedly died from divine retribution. An empire based in this city fell when Nabonidus lost the Battle of Opis. A king of this city established a law code with rules like \"an eye for an eye.\" A \"captivity\" of Jews named for this city ended when it was conquered by Cyrus the Great. For ten points, name this Mesopotamian city ruled by Hammurabi and home to the Hanging Gardens.", "answer": "<b><u>Babylon</u></b> (accept <b><u>Babil</u></b>im)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "In 1946, the Soviet Union prevented a production of this work \"on the grounds that the drama [would] inspire a [...] suicide wave.\" This play was first performed at McCarter Theatre in New Jersey before transferring to Broadway, where Edward Albee hailed it as \u201cthe greatest American play ever written.\u201d Told in three acts, this metatheatrical play features an omniscient stage manager who oversees the performance and is set in Grover's Corners, a \"typical American community.\" For ten points, name this play by Thornton Wilder, which earned him his first Pulitzer Prize for Drama.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Our Town</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Drama"}, {"question": "With his officers, this leader organized the Bayard Order to put on plays and patronize the arts. Voltaire revised this man's essay <em>Anti-Machiavel</em>, which was a scathing critique of cynicism in <em>The Prince</em>. This leader nearly ran away to England with his male lover, Hans Hermann von Katte, though he was caught and forced to watch Katte's execution by his father, Frederick William. For ten points, name this Crown Prince-turned-King of Prussia, who became famous for his military genius.", "answer": "<b><u>Frederick</u></b> the Great (or <b><u>Friedrich</u></b> der Gro\u00dfe [[\"GROSS\"-uh]]; accept <b><u>Frederick</u> </b>II; or <b><u>Friedrich</u></b> II; accept <b><u>Old Fritz</u></b>; or Der <b><u>Alte Fritz</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<em>Tarzan</em> creator Edgar Rice Burroughs's relative Kate Rice found gold deposits in this province at sites like Wekusko Lake and Thompson. The precursor to the Royal Mounted Police broke-up this province's \"General Strike of 1919\" which occurred following their participation in World War One. Led by Louis Real [[reh-AHL]], the Red River Rebellion resulted in the foundation of this province, the first carved from the Northwest Territories. The city of Winnipeg was the site of that rebellion in, for ten points, what Canadian province?", "answer": "<b><u>Manitoba</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This law's namesake representative introduced the Kinkaid Act to modify it, aiming to settle the Nebraska Sandhills. Grover Cleveland's last speech to Congress requested that this act be amended to allow the Indian Territory, now in modern Oklahoma, to be opened to prospective settlers. George Henry Evans supported the passage of this act by using the phrase \"Vote Yourself a Farm.\" 160 free acres of government land were offered to U.S. citizens by, for ten points, which 1862 act during the Lincoln administration?", "answer": "<b><u>Homestead</u></b> Act of 1862", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Through the Riverdale Agreement, this specific group integrated their Dominion counterparts in Canada, Australia, and New Zealand. Utilizing the bouncing bomb, a squadron of this military force known as the \"Dam Busters\" caused a flood in the Ruhr valley during Operation Chastise. In reference to this specific military force, Winston Churchill stated \"Never in the field of human conflict was so much owed by so many to so few\" following their clash with the Luftwaffe in the Battle of Britain. For ten points, name this air force of Britain during the Second World War and beyond.", "answer": "<b><u>Royal</u></b> Air Force (accept <b><u>RAF</u></b>; prompt on answers including descriptions of the \"British armed forces\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In this city, a student organization known as the Student Revolutionary Directorate committed an attack on the Presidential Palace and the Radio Reloj [[REH-loh]] simultaneously. Held at the Hotel Nacional, Meyer Lanskey organized a 1940s conference named for this this city which led to greater communication between America's organized crime families. Fulgencio Batista's resignation preceded for ten points, the capture of what Caribbean capital city by Che Guevara and Fidel Castro?", "answer": "<b><u>Havana</u></b> (accept La <b><u>Habana</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The first president of this university wrote a \"A Study of the Decay of Races Through the Survival of the Unfit.\" The founder of this university supported an effort planned by Theodore Judah. Originally founded as an agricultural institute, this university was created by a \"robber baron\" who controlled the Central and Southern Pacific railroads. A member of the \u201cBig Four,\" this school was damaged by a 1906 earthquake. Located in Palo Alto, for ten points, what private research university is located just outside of Silicon Valley?", "answer": "<b><u>Stanford</u></b> University", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A 3rd-century chamber containing a marble relief of this animal being killed was found in Walbrook Street in London in 1954. The castration of this animal became a central ritual and artistic motif in the 2nd-century <em>Magna Mater</em> cult. According to one cult, this animal was killed by the infant Mithra, whose worshippers re-enacted the slaughter. The Greeks believed that Zeus took the form of this animal to abduct Europa. For ten points, name this type of male cattle that ancient astronomers saw in the constellation Taurus.", "answer": "<b><u>Bull</u></b>s (prompt on <b><u>cattle</u></b> or <b><u>bovine</u></b>s; prompt on \"cow(s)\" until \"male\")", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "In this state, the discovery of the Goddard coin, which dates back to 11th-century Norway, is considered evidence that Vikings regularly traded with Native Americans. That artifact was discovered in this state's Penobscot Bay. The Webster-Ashburton Treaty fixed the borders shared by this state and the Maritime Province of New Brunswick. Until 1820, the state of Massachusetts directly controlled, for ten points, what New England state governed from Augusta?", "answer": "<b><u>Maine</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Largo citizen Robert Scott Palmer was given a 63 month sentence for participation in this event following his assault of an officer with a wooden plank. A blue suit worn by Representative Andy Kim was donated to the Smithsonian after a photo of him in it cleaning litter in the wake of this event went viral. Mitch McConnell openly condemned this event as a \"failed insurrection.\" A pro-Trump mob aimed to overturn the election by attempting to seize the title legislative house in, for ten points, which January 2021 attack?", "answer": "2021 United States <b><u>Capitol Attack</u></b> (accept \"Insurrection\" or \"Riot\" in place of \"Attack\")", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "The tide of a war on this continent was turned by Bocchus [[BOH-kus]] switching sides and betraying Jugurtha to Sulla. Cato the Younger killed himself on this continent, where Masinissa [[mahs-sih-NEES-uh]] united the kingdom of Numidia. Syphax [[SYE-fahx]] allied with Hasdrubal on this continent, where a decisive battle at Zama ended the Second Punic War. Scipio acquired an agnomen by defeating Hannibal on, for ten points, what continent, home to the city of Carthage and the Roman provinces of Mauretania and Egypt?", "answer": "<b><u>Africa</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>One way to circumvent this general project is Psiphon [[\"SIGH\"-fohn]], created</u></b> <b><u>by the Computer Science department of the University of Toronto. One part of this</u></b> <b><u>series of laws is the Golden Shield Project, a (+)</u> mass-surveillance and censoring system, supervised by the Public Security Bureau. This collection of legislation aims to prevent citizens from researching things like the Falun Gong or (*) </b>Xinjiang internment camps. For ten points, give this collective name for a series of legislation enforced by the People\u2019s Republic of China to regulate the domestic Internet.", "answer": "<b><u>Great Firewall</u></b> (or <b><u>F\u00e1nghu\u01d2 Ch\u00e1ngch\u00e9ng</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man fought in the Battle of Tecoac, where he defeated then-president</u></b> <b><u>Sebasti\u00e1n Lerdo de Tejada\u2019s forces and forced him into exile in New York. This man</u></b> <b><u>appointed his confidante, Juan N. (+)</u> M\u00e9ndez, as provisional president before becoming president himself for (*) </b>seven terms, filling bureaucratic positions with his allies, the <em>cientificos</em>. For ten points, name this general and politician who served seven terms over thirty years as President of Mexico.", "answer": "Porfirio <b><u>D\u00edaz</u></b> (or Jos\u00e9 de la Cruz Porfirio <b><u>D\u00edaz</u></b> Mori)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The tavern of Henry Fite served as the meeting house for this legislative body</u></b> <b><u>following William Howe's successful New York and New Jersey campaign. The Olive</u></b> <b><u>Branch (+)</u> Petition was drafted by this body. The Conway Cabal sent a letter to this governmental body meant to elevate Horatio Gates to major general by facilitating the sacking of George Washington. The Thirteen (*) </b>Colonies were governed by, for ten points, which legislative body during much of the Revolutionary War?", "answer": "(Second) <b><u>Continental Congress</u></b> (do not accept \"First Continental Congress\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A ruler of this name presided over the \"moderate decade\" and the \"progressive</u></b> <b><u>biennium,\" both named for the party in power. One ruler of this name ordered the</u></b> <b><u>execution of her court rival Hugh le (+)</u> Despenser. That ruler of this name allied with Roger Mortimer in a rebellion against her husband, Edward II. Along with her husband, a ruler of this name (*) </b>patronized the voyages of Christopher Columbus. For ten points, give this name of the Castilian queen who united Spain by marrying Ferdinand of Aragon.", "answer": "<b><u>Isabella</u></b> (accept Queen <b><u>Isabella</u></b> I; or Queen <b><u>Isabella</u></b> II; accept <b><u>Isabella</u></b> of France; or <b><u>Isabella</u></b> the She-Wolf)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this case, lawyer and personal friend of the defendant Robert Kardashian</u></b> <b><u>joined the so-called \"Dream Team\" of attorneys as to not be forced to testify against</u></b> <b><u>this case's accused party. Johnnie (+)</u> Cochran's closing argument of \"if the glove doesn't fit, you must acquit\" may have swayed the jury in this case in not finding one man guilty for killing Nicole Brown and Ronnie Goldman. A former Buffalo (*) </b>Bills running back was tried in LA during, for ten points, which 1995 murder case?", "answer": "O. J. <b><u>Simpson</u></b> murder case (or The People of the State of California v. Orenthal James <b><u>Simpson</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The predecessor to this weapon was intended to be used in the never-realized</u></b> <b><u>Operation Downfall. Operation Pacer IVY removed this weapon from one country and</u></b> <b><u>stored it on (+)</u> Johnston Atoll, after which it was destroyed in Operation Pacer HO. The tactical use of this weapon was tested during the Malayan Emergency, after which Secretary of State Dean Rusk suggested it could be used lawfully during another conflict. This carcinogenic (*) </b>chemical weapon was used to destroy high density foliage used by Viet Cong guerillas. For ten points, name this herbicide mixture heavily deployed by the United States during the Vietnam War.", "answer": "<b><u>Agent Orange</u></b> (or Herbicide <b><u>Orange</u></b>; accept <b><u>Rainbow</u></b> Herbicide or Agents <b><u>White</u></b>, <b><u>Blue</u></b>, <b><u>Purple</u></b>, <b><u>Pink</u></b>, or <b><u>Green</u></b> before \"Pacer\"; prompt on \"herbicide\" or \"defoliant\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A leader of a \"Circle\" named for this city, Moritz Schlick, was gunned down by a</u></b> <b><u>fascist-leaning former student who took offense to his anti-metaphysical philosophy.</u></b> <b><u>While attending the</u> </b><em><b><u>Realschule</u></b></em><b><u> [[ray-AHL-shoo-luh]] in this city, philosopher Ludwig</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> Wittgenstein [[VIT-gen-stine]] and Adolf Hitler were classmates together. Kurt G\u00f6del and Otto Neurath [[NOY-rath]] were members of the (*) </b><em>Wiener Kreis</em> [[VEE-nuh KRIZE]], a school of thought from, for ten points, which Austrian capital city?", "answer": "<b><u>Vienna</u></b> (accept <b><u>Vienna</u></b> Circle; accept <b><u>Wien</u></b>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this region's Gcwihaba [[guh-kwee-HAH-buh]] cave, hunter Hendrik van Zyl</u></b> <b><u>[[ZEEL]] supposedly stashed his entire fortune made from the ivory trade. The Khwe</u></b> <b><u>[[KWEH]] and Basarwa people, known collectively as (+)</u> \"Bushmen,\" first settled this desert region 22,000 years ago. Departing from the Transvaal, Boer explorers traversed this region during the \"Thirstland\" Trek in an attempt to colonize modern-day Angola. In order to escape the genocidal efforts of the (*) </b>German Empire, many Herero people crossed, for ten points, what southwest African desert's vast savannah?", "answer": "<b><u>Kalahari</u></b> Desert", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In his 30s, this man was paid lavish sums by MI5 to publish pro-war articles in</u></b> <b><u>the paper</u> </b><em><b><u>Il Popolo</u></b></em><b><u> and to send veterans to beat up peace protesters. This man, who</u></b> <b><u>once said \"Islam (+)</u> is a more effective religion than Christianity,\" signed the Lateran Treaty, which gave the papacy independent statehood. This leader formed the Pact of (*) </b>Steel with Nazi Germany. For ten points, name this creator of the Blackshirts known as \"Il Duce\" [[DO-cheh]], the Fascist dictator of Italy.", "answer": "Benito <b><u>Mussolini</u></b> (or Benito Amilcare Andrea <b><u>Mussolini</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}